<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Family | Joseph Bulger]]></title>
  <link href="http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/categories/family/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://josephbulger.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-09T18:46:13-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://josephbulger.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joseph Bulger]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Story of a Family Becoming Agile]]></title>
    <link href="http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/2009/12/16/story-of-a-family-becoming-agile/"/>
    <updated>2009-12-16T05:54:18-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/2009/12/16/story-of-a-family-becoming-agile</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m going to be making my family “agile” in the upcoming weeks. What does that mean exactly? Well, I’ll be posting more about it, but essentially we’re going to organize our family activities around agile principles. These are software management principles that I have been studying (and trying to apply) for a number of years now. They have proven to be very effective at my work, and I can see how they would be equally effective at home, as well.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p></p>

<p>So what exactly am I talking about? Let’s take a look. I’m going to start out by making a cork board for our family. It should look something like this:</p>

<p><a href="/images/posts/2009/12/agileFamily2.png"><img src="/images/posts/2009/12/agileFamily_thumb.png" alt="agileFamily" /></a></p>

<p>Colored cards are “shared” cards. That means any parent can do them. Children also have a daily card. These are things they have to do every day, and they check them off when they’re done.</p>

<p>When we actually get the board I’ll post up some pics and explanation.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Look What My Kid Did at Target Yesterday]]></title>
    <link href="http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/2009/03/15/look-what-my-kid-did-at-target-yesterday/"/>
    <updated>2009-03-15T10:22:16-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/2009/03/15/look-what-my-kid-did-at-target-yesterday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Apparently Chuchi was having a field day at Target the other day, check out these pictures…</p>

<p><a href="http://cid-5347824229f455ab.skydrive.live.com/redir.aspx?page=browse&amp;resid=5347824229F455AB!153&amp;ct=photos"><img src="/images/posts/2009/03/inlinerepresentationba83fe7ed842433698404ef95d58ac36.jpg" alt="View Chuchi at Target" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://cid-5347824229f455ab.skydrive.live.com/redir.aspx?page=browse&amp;resid=5347824229F455AB!153&amp;ct=photos">View Full Album</a></p>

<p>That’s where you see the shots of him with his mouth wide open. What you can’t see is his hand gestures. Yes, he’s actually doing poses. Kind of freaks me out a little bit. At first he was just playing around with my wife with the hat and the glasses, but then he saw me taking picture and he actually started posing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
