<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: About | Joseph Bulger]]></title>
  <link href="http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/categories/about/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://josephbulger.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-04T21:00:01-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://josephbulger.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joseph Bulger]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[And So It Begins]]></title>
    <link href="http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/2009/03/06/hello-world/"/>
    <updated>2009-03-06T08:43:15-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/2009/03/06/hello-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to <strong>JosephBulger.com</strong>!  This is hopefully going to be the first of many blogs that I write!  This blog will focus on things that I take interest of mostly: my family, programming, various technologies, etc.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>My Family</h2>

<p>Needless to say, this is where the majority of my time and effort are spent!  So naturally, I&rsquo;ll be blogging a great deal about my family.</p>

<p>My wonderful wife, Michelle, takes care of our entire family, which is completely unbelievable.  She&rsquo;s also running  a <a href="http://www.cookingwithmichelle.com">blog.</a></p>

<p>Sarah is just finishing up 4rth grade! </p>

<p>Joseph is talking/walking/running/anything like crazy and Isaac has nearly mastered the art of walking and is moving onto the science of speaking.</p>

<h2>Programming</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ll be writing a lot of blogs about programming concepts and their applications that I come across in my work.</p>

<h2><a href="http://www.rockdigitalconsulting.com">RockDigital Consulting</a> </h2>

<p>I work full time as a Senior Software Engineer, but I also run a consulting company on the side that I might write about preiodically as well.  Sound like a plug?  You bet it is =P  Sorry, have to get my advertising in when I can!  Anything cool and exciting that happens to my company I&rsquo;ll most likely blog about so people can see what&rsquo;s happening there.</p>

<h2>Technologies</h2>

<p>This could really be about anything, but its most likely going to be cool gadgets, ideas, frameworks I&rsquo;m looking into or using.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
