<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Learning Ruby | Joseph Bulger]]></title>
  <link href="http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/categories/learning-ruby/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://josephbulger.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-09T18:57:42-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://josephbulger.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joseph Bulger]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning Ruby on Rails: Installing RubyMine]]></title>
    <link href="http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/2011/05/21/learning-ruby-on-rails-installing-rubymine/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-21T14:28:29-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/2011/05/21/learning-ruby-on-rails-installing-rubymine</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>RubyMine is a Jetbrains product for developing ruby applications.  I use a lot of Jetbrains products, which is why I&rsquo;m giving RubyMine a run through.  I&rsquo;m hoping it will be as good as their other products. Since I&rsquo;m a .NET developer, I&rsquo;m thinking it will help me bridge the gap between the typical environment I&rsquo;m used to using (Visual Studio 2010) and RoR.<!-- more --></p>

<p>Now, before we get to install RubyMine, there is one caveat that we have to take care of.  You have to have a java runtime on your linux distro in order to run RubyMine, but it can <strong>not </strong>be OpenJDK, so if you have that installed (I did), then you have to uninstall it first, and install another one.</p>

<p>For example:</p>

<blockquote><p>$ sudo apt-get install sun-java6-jre sun-java6-jdk</p></blockquote>

<p>My screencast will <strong>not </strong>include this step, because I actually need java installed on my linux distro to <strong>make </strong>the screencast.</p>

<p>Once you have java installed go to <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/ruby/download/index.html">http://www.jetbrains.com/ruby/download/index.html</a> and download RubyMine.</p>

<p>I downloaded it into my home directory.</p>

<p>After you&rsquo;ve downloaded it, then you need to extract it</p>

<blockquote><p>$ tar -xvzf rubymine-2.0.2.tar.gz</p></blockquote>

<p>And move it to the opt folder</p>

<blockquote><p>$ sudo mv rubymine93.202 /opt/rubymine</p></blockquote>

<p>Now we need to add an link to our java runtime so RubyMine will be able to see it</p>

<blockquote><p>$ sudo ln -s /usr/bin/java /bin/java</p></blockquote>

<p>I also went ahead and added a shortcut to my panel so I can open it easily.</p>

<p><img src="http://media.tumblr.com/tumblr_l6f7y4c2T61qbyy0y.png" alt="Adding a shotcut" /></p>

<p><img src="http://media.tumblr.com/tumblr_l6f87jErnk1qbyy0y.png" alt="There’s an icon at /opt/rubymine/bin/RMlogo.svg" /></p>

<p><img src="http://media.tumblr.com/tumblr_l6f8efWaJW1qbyy0y.png" alt="Setting RubyMine Starting Point" /></p>

<p>And here&rsquo;s a video of the whole thing:</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning Ruby on Rails: Installing Ruby on Rails]]></title>
    <link href="http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/2011/05/17/learning-ruby-on-rails-installing-ruby/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-17T14:18:16-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/2011/05/17/learning-ruby-on-rails-installing-ruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Next up on the list is installing Ruby on our Ubuntu instance.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>First thing we need to do is to run an update on Ubuntu to make sure we have all our tools up to date.</p>

<blockquote><p>sudo apt-get update</p></blockquote>

<p>Then install aptitude and do an update on it. Aptitude is a new package management system for ubuntu.</p>

<blockquote><p>sudo apt-get aptitude
sudo aptitude update</p></blockquote>

<p>After that we&rsquo;re going to need to install Git and curl which we can do by running</p>

<blockquote><p>sudo aptitude install build-essential git-core curl</p></blockquote>

<p>We need Git and curl because we&rsquo;re going to be using them in order to bring down the RVM (Ruby Version Manager), which will be what we&rsquo;re using to install Ruby.</p>

<p>To install the RVM you need to run this command</p>

<blockquote><p>bash &lt; &lt;(curl -s <a href="https://rvm.beginrescueend.com/install/rvm">https://rvm.beginrescueend.com/install/rvm</a>)</p></blockquote>

<p>And then you will need to edit a file to have Ubuntu point scripts in the right place with these two commands</p>

<blockquote><p>echo &lsquo;[[ -s &ldquo;$HOME/.rvm/scripts/rvm&rdquo; ]] &amp;&amp; source &ldquo;$HOME/.rvm/scripts/rvm&rdquo;&rsquo; >> ~/.bashrc</p></blockquote>

<p>Then you will need to close your terminal and open up a new one</p>

<p>The next thing we&rsquo;ll need to do is to install a handful of other packages that we&rsquo;ll need for ruby to work (all in one line on the terminal!)</p>

<blockquote><p>sudo aptitude install build-essential bison openssl libreadline6 libreadline6-dev
curl git-core zlib1g zlib1g-dev libssl-dev libyaml-dev libsqlite3-0
libsqlite3-dev sqlite3 libxml2-dev libxslt-dev autoconf</p></blockquote>

<p>And at this point we&rsquo;re ready to actually install Ruby</p>

<blockquote><p>rvm install 1.9.2</p></blockquote>

<p>After its installed we can tell RVM to use this version as the default ruby implementation from now on by saying</p>

<blockquote><p>rvm &mdash;default use 1.9.2</p></blockquote>

<p>And you can verify that by executing</p>

<blockquote><p>ruby -v</p></blockquote>

<p>Next thing to do is install Rails</p>

<blockquote><p>gem install rails</p></blockquote>

<p>At this point you now have rails running on your box.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s very easy to get a sample rails server up and running. Go to your terminal and run the following</p>

<blockquote><p>rails new myapp
cd myapp
bundle install</p></blockquote>

<p>And once all the gems get installed for your app you can start your server up by</p>

<blockquote><p>rails server</p></blockquote>

<p>You&rsquo;ll need to right click on the url link and open it up in your browser to see.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning Ruby on Rails: Installing Ubuntu as a VM]]></title>
    <link href="http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/2011/05/17/learning-ruby-on-rails-installing-ubuntu-as-a-vm/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-17T09:58:02-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/2011/05/17/learning-ruby-on-rails-installing-ubuntu-as-a-vm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Installing Ubuntu as a VM is vastly simpler (and faster) than installing any Windows distro.</p>

<p>As an aside, I&rsquo;m using VMWare&rsquo;s Workstation product, in case you&rsquo;re wondering what VM software I use, but you could do this just as easily with other products.</p>

<!-- more -->


<ol>
<li> Go to Ubuntu and grab the <a href="http://www.ubuntu.com/download">latest version</a></li>
<li> Kick up a new VM

<ol>
<li>Choose a Typical Install</li>
<li>Choose to Install from disk (iso) file</li>
<li>Pick the iso you just downloaded</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li> Run through the installation process on your VM</li>
</ol>


<p>Once you have Ubuntu up and running it&rsquo;s probably going to ask you to apply some updates, but aside from that you&rsquo;re done!</p>

<p>I made a video of this whole process.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning Ruby on Rails: A C# Programmer's Perspective]]></title>
    <link href="http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/2011/05/17/learning-ruby-on-rails-a-c-programmers-perspective/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-17T08:11:12-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/2011/05/17/learning-ruby-on-rails-a-c-programmers-perspective</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been doing C# programming for some time now.  I&rsquo;ve been investigating Ruby and talking to coworkers about it, but have yet to really dive in and start learning the language and it&rsquo;s web counterpart, Rails.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I recently came up with a fun concept that I wanted to try on the web and see how people liked it, and I thought it would be a great opportunity to try learning Ruby on Rails.  This will be a series of blog posts on my trials as a primarily Windows C# developer working with this new language and new stack.</p>

<p>Before I begin, I&rsquo;m going to outline at a high level what I&rsquo;m planning on doing.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m going to install a virtual machine with <a href="http://www.ubuntu.com/">Ubuntu </a>and run my ruby environment on that.  I know I could do this on Windows, but I recently had an experience with loading up <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/teamcity/">TeamCity </a>on a derivation of CentOS and it was delightfully easy.  It&rsquo;s made me realize that if I&rsquo;m going to be developing a Ruby on Rails app that more than likely when I go to deploy this app it will probably end up being easier if my local environment is close to what host environment I will be having.  And I will definitely be pushing my app out to a Linux distro, so therefore Ubuntu is my choice for my local OS.</p>

<p>Next, I&rsquo;ll be using <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/ruby/">RubyMine </a>as my IDE. I know there&rsquo;s a lot of ruby devs out there using <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vim_%28text_editor%29">VIM</a>, but I haven&rsquo;t ventured into that family of text editors yet, and although I&rsquo;m aware it has features that are very compelling, it&rsquo;s probably too much for me to take on at this point.  After a while, when I start feeling comfortable in Ubuntu and RubyMine I might venture into the VIM space and see how that goes.</p>

<p>I plan to deploy the app using <a href="http://www.heroku.com/">Heroku</a>.  I don&rsquo;t have the desire to setup up a production stack.  I do it enough with my windows applications, and I&rsquo;m growing more and more tired of doing this.  In retrospect, at this point it feels as if it&rsquo;s a solved problem, and for me Heroku does the job of being a service that solves it quite nicely for me to not worry about anything.</p>

<p>Up next in this series will be a step by step of how I set up my VM with Ubuntu.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
