<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Wireless | Joseph Bulger]]></title>
  <link href="http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/categories/wireless/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://josephbulger.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-09T18:57:42-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://josephbulger.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joseph Bulger]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wireless Adapter Traps]]></title>
    <link href="http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/2011/08/08/wireless-adapter-traps/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-08T04:00:39-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/2011/08/08/wireless-adapter-traps</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ok so you go to the store and you&rsquo;re looking around for an awesome deal on a Wireless-N adapter, and you find one for only $14!  "How can this be!?&ldquo; you might ask yourself?  Well, let me explain something to you before you end up with the same situation I find myself in right now.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Ok so my story goes a little differently than that, but it&rsquo;s basically the same thing.  My wife needed a new wireless adapter for her computer because the one she had was pathetically bad.</p>

<p>So, me being the tech nerd that I am, decided</p>

<blockquote><p>why not buy a Wireless-N adapter so when I upgrade my router in the next year or so she&rsquo;ll already be ready for it?</p></blockquote>

<p>So I went and got her a <a href="http://www.dlink.com/products/?pid=722">DLink DWA-125</a>.  Not only that but the price tag on the sucker was only like $14, which I thought was amazing.  Not until I <a href="/blog/2011/08/07/linksys-e4200-retrospective/">upgraded my router</a> did I realize the error of my ways.  It&rsquo;s in the bands people, the bands will get you every time.</p>

<p>So I bought the adapter because it&rsquo;s Wireless-N.  And it is, don&rsquo;t get me wrong.  However, the bands it operates on are&hellip; well.. I should say&hellip; the <strong>band</strong> it operates on, is 2.4 GHz.  You might be thinking, &ldquo;what&rsquo;s the big deal Joe? Just connect to your router and go with it man.&rdquo;  Here&rsquo;s the problem. When you connect a device that runs G to a network that already has a device running on N, a couple things could happen.</p>

<p>You could be dropped to Wireless-G, and both adapters would run there.  Which kind of defeats the purpose of buying the N adapter, don&rsquo;t you think?</p>

<p>Or&hellip; Your network could go crazy and let the adapters battle it out, which is what happened to me.  Who won you might ask?  No one, because every time one of the adapters would lose connection, it would just try to get it back, which would essentially kick the other one off, etc. etc.</p>

<p>So be aware when purchasing N adapters.  If you&rsquo;re like me and you have G devices that you<strong> still need to use</strong>, then you better get an N adapter that runs on a 5GHz band. How do you know if your router can handle this set up?  Well&hellip; <a href="/blog/2011/08/07/linksys-e4200-retrospective/">that&rsquo;s a different story</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Linksys E4200: Retrospective]]></title>
    <link href="http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/2011/08/07/linksys-e4200-retrospective/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-07T12:25:13-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/2011/08/07/linksys-e4200-retrospective</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just recently retired my <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linksys_WRT54G_series">WRT54G</a> in favor or a Wireless N Router.  I ended up going with the <a href="http://homestore.cisco.com/en-us/Routers/Linksys-E4200-MaximumPerformance-Wirelessn-router_stcVVproductId122703236VVcatId551966VVviewprod.htm">Linksys E4200</a> for a number of reasons.<!-- more --></p>

<p>First of all, it&rsquo;s a high performance router, and so far it&rsquo;s lived up to that expectation.  What do I mean by a high performance router?</p>

<blockquote><p>It&rsquo;s capable of handling 450 Mbps on the 5GHz band.</p></blockquote>

<p>We&rsquo;ll get to the band in a second.  This is going to be extremely useful for me later on when I start setting up a NAS in my house to stream content.</p>

<p>Secondly, it&rsquo;s a dual band router.  What exactly is a dual band router? It&rsquo;s pretty simple actually.</p>

<blockquote><p>The router has the ability to host two networks (3 if you include the guest network): one on a 5GHz band, and another on a 2.4 GHz band.</p></blockquote>

<p>Now, there are a couple catches here.  First, this router is a <strong>true</strong> dual band router.  What I mean by that is that it can run both bands <strong>simulataneously</strong>.  If you&rsquo;re in the market for a new router, you have to keep this in mind because you could be looking at a router that says it&rsquo;s dual band, but when you bring it home, it can&rsquo;t run them both at the same time, you have to choose which one to roll with.</p>

<p>For me, I have to have both bands up at the same time, which brings me to the second catch.  If you have devices (PCs, IPods, IPhones, Androids, etc.)  then it&rsquo;s likely that some are going to run on Wireless-G and some have Wireless-N.  In my household, most of the devices run on Wireless-G, and I have a couple that can run Wireless-N.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the catch.  If you have a Wireless-N capable router and you have devices that are connecting to it via Wireless-G and Wireless-N <strong>on the same band</strong>, then the router has to choose the lesser of the two, which means everyone on that band is stuck on Wireless-G.  This goes for all routers, by the way.  This is where the two bands come into play.  If you have two bands, you can set one band up to run Wireless-N (5 GHz), and you can set up the other to be Wireless-G (2 GHz).</p>

<p>This brings me to the first complaint that I have about the E4200.  When I originally set up the router, I <strong>assumed</strong> that the router would be configured out of the box to handle the exact scenario that I described previously.  However, what I came to find out was that my router, out of the box, was configured in some kind of Mixed Mode setting for <strong>both bands</strong>.  This wreaked havoc on my network for a day or two because I didn&rsquo;t realize what was going on, and chalked it up to Comcast screwing with my internet again (they have a tendency to do this).  However, after sitting down for a second and thinking about it, I decided to go digging around in the settings and that&rsquo;s when I discovered the mixed mode issue.</p>

<p>This wouldn&rsquo;t have normally been a problem, except for one thing:</p>

<blockquote><p>I have a couple of devices at home that are Wireless-N but they only operate on the 2.4 GHz band.</p></blockquote>

<p>This caused a war to ensue on the router between my G devices and my N devices, the winner being no one. Long story short, I ended up doing a manual set up on my router, where the 5GHz band was configured to run only Wireless-N and the 2.4 GHz band was configured Wireless-G only.  Why did I do it that way?  Because Wireless-G devices can only operate on 2.4 GHz band, and the devices that I have that only handle Wireless-N on the 2.4 band automatically negotiate down to Wireless-G when connecting to the router on 2.4 now, which is what would happen to them anyway.</p>

<p>Once I did that the war ended and now everything is playing nicely together.  There has been one other snag along the way, but I&rsquo;ll save that for another post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
