<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Install | Joseph Bulger]]></title>
  <link href="http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/categories/install/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://josephbulger.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-09T18:46:13-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://josephbulger.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joseph Bulger]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning Ruby on Rails: Installing Ruby on Rails]]></title>
    <link href="http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/2011/05/17/learning-ruby-on-rails-installing-ruby/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-17T14:18:16-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/2011/05/17/learning-ruby-on-rails-installing-ruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Next up on the list is installing Ruby on our Ubuntu instance.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>First thing we need to do is to run an update on Ubuntu to make sure we have all our tools up to date.</p>

<blockquote><p>sudo apt-get update</p></blockquote>

<p>Then install aptitude and do an update on it. Aptitude is a new package management system for ubuntu.</p>

<blockquote><p>sudo apt-get aptitude
sudo aptitude update</p></blockquote>

<p>After that we&rsquo;re going to need to install Git and curl which we can do by running</p>

<blockquote><p>sudo aptitude install build-essential git-core curl</p></blockquote>

<p>We need Git and curl because we&rsquo;re going to be using them in order to bring down the RVM (Ruby Version Manager), which will be what we&rsquo;re using to install Ruby.</p>

<p>To install the RVM you need to run this command</p>

<blockquote><p>bash &lt; &lt;(curl -s <a href="https://rvm.beginrescueend.com/install/rvm">https://rvm.beginrescueend.com/install/rvm</a>)</p></blockquote>

<p>And then you will need to edit a file to have Ubuntu point scripts in the right place with these two commands</p>

<blockquote><p>echo &lsquo;[[ -s &ldquo;$HOME/.rvm/scripts/rvm&rdquo; ]] &amp;&amp; source &ldquo;$HOME/.rvm/scripts/rvm&rdquo;&rsquo; >> ~/.bashrc</p></blockquote>

<p>Then you will need to close your terminal and open up a new one</p>

<p>The next thing we&rsquo;ll need to do is to install a handful of other packages that we&rsquo;ll need for ruby to work (all in one line on the terminal!)</p>

<blockquote><p>sudo aptitude install build-essential bison openssl libreadline6 libreadline6-dev
curl git-core zlib1g zlib1g-dev libssl-dev libyaml-dev libsqlite3-0
libsqlite3-dev sqlite3 libxml2-dev libxslt-dev autoconf</p></blockquote>

<p>And at this point we&rsquo;re ready to actually install Ruby</p>

<blockquote><p>rvm install 1.9.2</p></blockquote>

<p>After its installed we can tell RVM to use this version as the default ruby implementation from now on by saying</p>

<blockquote><p>rvm &mdash;default use 1.9.2</p></blockquote>

<p>And you can verify that by executing</p>

<blockquote><p>ruby -v</p></blockquote>

<p>Next thing to do is install Rails</p>

<blockquote><p>gem install rails</p></blockquote>

<p>At this point you now have rails running on your box.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s very easy to get a sample rails server up and running. Go to your terminal and run the following</p>

<blockquote><p>rails new myapp
cd myapp
bundle install</p></blockquote>

<p>And once all the gems get installed for your app you can start your server up by</p>

<blockquote><p>rails server</p></blockquote>

<p>You&rsquo;ll need to right click on the url link and open it up in your browser to see.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning Ruby on Rails: Installing Ubuntu as a VM]]></title>
    <link href="http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/2011/05/17/learning-ruby-on-rails-installing-ubuntu-as-a-vm/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-17T09:58:02-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://josephbulger.github.io/blog/2011/05/17/learning-ruby-on-rails-installing-ubuntu-as-a-vm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Installing Ubuntu as a VM is vastly simpler (and faster) than installing any Windows distro.</p>

<p>As an aside, I&rsquo;m using VMWare&rsquo;s Workstation product, in case you&rsquo;re wondering what VM software I use, but you could do this just as easily with other products.</p>

<!-- more -->


<ol>
<li> Go to Ubuntu and grab the <a href="http://www.ubuntu.com/download">latest version</a></li>
<li> Kick up a new VM

<ol>
<li>Choose a Typical Install</li>
<li>Choose to Install from disk (iso) file</li>
<li>Pick the iso you just downloaded</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li> Run through the installation process on your VM</li>
</ol>


<p>Once you have Ubuntu up and running it&rsquo;s probably going to ask you to apply some updates, but aside from that you&rsquo;re done!</p>

<p>I made a video of this whole process.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
